Guide to the Loren Cameron papers, 1961-2008
Cameron, Loren papers, 1961-2008
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Loren Cameron papers, 1961-2008, bulk 1993-2003
7677
Loren Cameron, 1959-
4.5 cubic feet
Manuscripts, photographs, published material, awards, videotapes.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The Loren Cameron Papers consist of photographic portraits created by Loren Cameron, correspondence and other manuscript material specifically documenting the Female to Male transsexual community.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Female to male transsexual and photographer of transgendered bodies. Loren Rex Cameron is a native Californian. Self-taught as a photographer and artist, he began producing self-portraits and images of transgender people in 1993. By 1995 his work had been shown in solo exhibitions in San Francisco, Minneapolis, and Los Angeles. His first photographic book, Body Alchemy: Transsexual Portraits was published in 1996, winning two Lambda Literary awards (Inaugural Transgender Category and Small Press Category, 1997). In 2001, he published his second publication, an electronic book on the World Wide Web, Man Tool: The Nuts and Bolts of Female-To-Male Surgery (Zero eBooks). Cameron is celebrated for his seminal work of transgender self-representation in the photographic arts. As a guest speaker, Cameron lectures extensively throughout the United States at community venues, colleges, universities, and art schools. In about 2000, he started using his middle name Rex.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Photographs from his first body of work "Our Vision, Our Voices," 1993, and from "God's Will," 1994. Correspondence to and from galleries, publishers, and others about Cameron's work, reviews, fan mail, viewers' comments from a 1998 exhibit, magazines and books that feature his work, and postcards advertising various exhibits. Some personal material including an annotated high school yearbook (1976, Dover Arkansas), a 20th year reunion booklet, and family photos. Awards, including the 1997 FTM International Pride Award and 2 Lambda Literary Awards for "Body Alchemy" in 1996, one for Transgender and one for the Small Press category. Six videos, including "Transsexuals Speak Out," a "60 Minutes" segment, and "You Don't Know Dick."
Paper copy of Cameron's 2001 online book, Man Tool, one of three, signed. Also, a 2002 resume; a printout of online interview of artist and exhibit curator Steve Compton from the Queer Arts Resource Forum; and a 2002 paper by Tee A. Corinne, "The Transiting Self: The Nude Self-Portraits of Transman Loren Cameron and Hermaphrodyke Del LaGrace Volcano," delivered at the College Art Association conference, February 21, 2002, as part of the session "How Do Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgendered Artists Address the Nude?"
Twenty 11"x14" silver gelatin photographs from Cameron's 1996 "Body Alchemy" project and text on foam core that accompanied their exhibit at Cornell University, April 19, 2002.
Unbound copy of Cuerpos Fotografiados por Cameron Vols. I & II, dated 2003.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cameron, Loren, 1959-; Cameron, Loren, 1959- Man tool.
Subjects:
Transsexualism--United States; Transsexuals--United States--Portraits; Gender identity.; Masculinity.; Body image.; Body size.; Photography of men--United States.; Photographers.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
One folder of correspondence in the accession folder has been RESTRICTED until 2024.
RELATED MATERIAL
Additional works by Loren Cameron are cataloged individually.
Online Alchemy the Art of Loren Cameron, a website by Loren Cameron.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Personal Material
Box 1, Box 2, Box 6
Series I consists of personal materials, including resumes, photos of family and friends, family correspondence, yearbooks, etc.
Series II. Projects
Box 1, Box 2, Box 4, Box 6
Series III. Exhibitions
Box 1, Box 2 Box 4-6
Series III contains materials from various exhibits of Cameron's work, including publicity and viewers' comments/correspondence. Also included are prints from Cameron's "Body Alchemy" exhibit.
Series IV. Correspondence, Reviews and Articles
Box 1, Box 2, Box 6
Series IV consists of reviews and articles regarding Cameron's work, along with miscellaneous correspondence. Correspondence regarding speaking engagements, and feedback from those engagements, is also included.
Series V. Magazines
Box 2
Series V contains magazines with articles about Loren Cameron, or about his work.
Series VI. Awards
Box 3
Series VII. Videos
Box 2
Series VII contains videos on transgender issues. Some of the videos have Cameron in them, and some are produced by Cameron.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Personal Material
  - Family Photos, 1961-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - High School Yearbook, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 20th Year High School Reunion Memory Book, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Resume, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter from Nancy Cameron, Loren's stepmother, March 2003 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Card from Susan Cameron-Tarleton, Loren's sister, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Brochure and paper on spiritualism, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Ad for Crawler Bumpers, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Misc. photos and family crest ring design, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Photos include images of Loren's apartment and Suzuki Samurai, his dog bix, his partner Stephanie, and 2 photographs of Loren and Cameron (Loren's MTF sister).
  - Change of name and gender forms (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Family correspondence, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Biography and CV, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Medical information, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Taboo Series 4, Episode 3 "Gender Benders" (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Beyond Productions, a National Geographic series
  - Feliz Navidad card from Roberto J. Edwards, October 12, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Massage Therapy documents, 1989-2012 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Life documents and certificates, 1959-2007 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Drawing of a centaur (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Nancy Kelly Cameron's obituary, September 24, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Cameron, L.R. Cameron's sister (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Catania, L.R. Cameron's sister (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - FTM group marches at the 1989 San Francisco Gay Pride Parade (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Photograph of Cameron marching with the banner "FTM", taken by photographer Howard Schatz (most noted for his fine art photographs of ballet dancers underwater). This was the first time an FTM group had ever walked in the parade. Cameron organized the participation and led the small group of FTMs. Cameron made the banner.
  - Personal Photographs (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Photographs of Cameron and partner Stephanie, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    Photos taken in Arkansas on Mt. Nebo near Dardanelle and in Russellville and Dover.
  - Items removed from individually catalogued books, 1994, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    Includes letter from Diane Wood Middlebrook removed from Loren's inscribed copy of Anne Sexton: A Biography. Also a letter from Minnie Bruce Pratt and a Firebrand Books card removed from Loren's inscribed copy of S/HE.
  - Photograph of Cantania Cameron Saltzman, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Cameron flying (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Cameron's dog, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of visit to Stepmother and Father's farm in Dover, AZ., 2003 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "Book letters", personal narrative, 1997-2001 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Tradeswomen calendar, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Marjorie Cameron material, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Last book proofs for vol. 1 and 2 of Cuerpos Pintados (Box 7)
  - 5 slide boxes of photographs, 2003, 2005 (Box 7)
- Series II. Projects
  - God's Will, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - E Book - Man Tool: The Nuts and Bolts of Female-to-Male Surgery, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Proposal for Man Tool: The Nuts and Bolts of Female-to-Male Surgery, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - DVD-1146 Transgender Nudes Collection Preview DVD, August 1, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - DVD-1147 Transgender Nudes Collection Test DVD, August 7, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - DVD-1148 Transgender Nudes Gallery DVD, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - "On Our Backs" photograph, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Photographs by Cameron, 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Triptych slides, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    These are the only copies of these slides.
  - Daniel Nicoletta: Photographs of Cameron, April 1, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Daniel Nicoletta: Photographs of Cameron, April 1, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Daniel Nicoletta: Photographs of Cameron, April 1, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Daniel Nicoletta: Photographs of Cameron, April 1, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Daniel Nicoletta: Photographs of Cameron, April 1, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - "Loren Cameron" by Daniel Nicoletta, October 22, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - "Loren and Yogi" by Daniel Nicoletta, January 7, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Zip Disk, ZD-7, - Digital Photography, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Triptych posters-framed (Box 4)
    Three framed items, original and only copies
  - "Cameron and Cameron", 2000 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "Samantha" by Loren Rex Cameron, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of unknown model (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - "Loren Cameron" by Daniel Nicoletta, October 22, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Cuerpos Fotografiados por Cameron I (unbound), 2003 (Box 6, Folder 8-10)
  - Cuerpos Fotografiados por Cameron II (unbound), 2003 (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
- Series III. Exhibitions
  - Viewers Comments - University of California, Santa Cruz, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Our Vision, Our Voices: Transsexual Portraits and Nudes, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 9-12)
  - Postcards, 1997-2001 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Presentation proposal packet, Nov. 2002 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Exhibits and presentations, correspondence and ads, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
  - Neoqueer exhibition materials, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Beyond XY: Four Photographers Explore the Masculine Continuum, June 26-August 7, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Centro Galego Arte Contemporanea, February 10-August 26, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - "Our Vision, Our Voices" Photographs, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - "Our Vision, Our Voices" opening-flyer and event photographs, May 2-31, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Body Alchemy Transsexual Portraits, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 1-20)
  - Body Alchemy Transsexual Portraits - Captions and Texts, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 1-20)
  - Photographs featured in original exhibition of "Body Alchemy", 1994-1995 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    This work was first exhibited (the first half of it before Cameron completed the second half for the book during the spring of 1996) at 848 Divasadero Community Art Space in San Francisco, California. It was later exhibited at 509 Community Center in San Francisco(luggage storage annex, a notable non-profit gallery on Market Street). It was completed and exhibited January-February 1997 in celebration of the publication of the work in September 1996 by Cleis Press.
  - Photos from Body Alchemy exhibit, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Additional art prints, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Series IV. Correspondence, Reviews and Articles
  - Correspondence from "Lisa" [ RESTRICTED], 2004
    This is in the accession folder.
  - Binder Number 1-1, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Binder Number 1-2, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Binder Number 1-3, 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Binder Number 1-4, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Binder Number 1-5, 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Binder Number 1-6, 1993-2001 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Binder Number 1-7, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Binder Number 1-8, 1992-1997 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Binder Number 1-9 Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Binder Number 2-1, 1993-1998 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Binder Number 2-2, 1995-2001 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Binder Number 2-3, 1995-2001 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Stephen Whittle, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Binder Number 3-1, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Binder Number 3-2, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Binder Number 3-3, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Binder Number 3-4, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - E Mail, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 32-33)
  - E Mail, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
  - Interview Steve Compton, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - The Transiting Self, Tee A. Corinne, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Letter re: Body Alchemy, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Bisexual Spaces, pp.129-134,144, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Man Tool, correspondence and ads, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Other correspondence, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence with Diane Middlebrook, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Flyers from appearances and presentations, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Finnish magazine Z, containg an article on transgender issues which mentions Loren Cameron, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence and publicity regarding Cameron's speaking engagements (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Advocate article on Cameron, December 19, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 2001, 2005, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Publicity materials (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence with Sarah Lazin, February 18, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Disclosure Magazine review, May-June 2001 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    Written about Cameron's work while being exhibited at the Clement Gallery, University of Toledo, Ohio, January-February 2001.
  - Howard Schatz Photography business card (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Cuerpos Pintados II review by Peter Mason, June 1997 (Box 2, Folder 60)
- Series V. Magazines
  - Advocate, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bang, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - B-Glad, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Camerawork: A Journal of Photographic Arts, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Circles, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Citizen K International, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Deneuve, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Diva, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Fabula, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - FTM Newsletter, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Gay Times, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Girlfriends, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Human Sexuality, 1997/1998 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - HX for Her, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Marie Claire, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Next Magazine, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - New Yorker, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - On our Backs, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Out, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Puckered Up, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Toledo City Paper, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Utne Reader, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Time magazine, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    With story on Roberto Edwards
- Series VI. Awards
  - Lambada Literary Award - Small Press, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Lambada Literary Award - Transgender, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - FTM International Pride Award, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series VII. Videos
  - "You Don't Know Dick: Courageous Hearts of Transsexual Men", V-555 (Box 2)
  - 60 Minutes plus "Diva Living", V-556 (Box 2)
  - Japanese news segment, V-557 (Box 2)
  - "Transsexuals Speak Out!" Panel Discussion (produced by Loren Cameron and Tony Boersma), V-558 (Box 2)
    Includes James Green, Susan Spyker, Kiki Whitlock, Sgt. Stephan Thorn.
  - "Transsexuals Speak Out!" Tony Boersma, editor, Master S-VHS, V-559 (Box 2)
  - Q.T.V. Santa Cruz news segment, V-560 (Box 2)
  - "Sex Change: Him to Her" Episode 1, October 2, 2005; V-4219 (Box 2)
  - "Sex Change: Him to Her" Episode 2, October 2, 2005; V-4220 (Box 2)
  - Kenneth Anger's Magic Lantern Cycle, V-5319 (Box 2)
    Cameron's aunt Marjorie is in the film
  - Sunset Strip, V-5320 (Box 2)
    Loren's sister Cameron is in the film
  - Cameron on "Inside Edition", V-5321 (Box 2)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged individually:
Anne Sexton: A Biography by Diane Wood Middlebrook, 1991. Signed by the author on the title page, also inscribed to Loren by the author on the front free endpaper. A laid in letter from Middlebrook to Loren was removed and is in Box 2 Folder 63. Middlebrook endorsed the back cover of Loren Cameron's book Body Alchemy.
Information for the Female to Male Cross Dresser and Transexual by Lou Sullivan, third edition October 1990. Inscribed by the author to Loren. Sullivan signed this book to Cameron before he went through dissolution (died). Cameron met him in the very beginning of Cameron's transition and attended the first FTM support gropus that Sullivan organized. This is the organization known as FTM International that was last expanded by Sullivan's chosen successor, Jameson Green.
S/HE by Minnie Bruce Pratt, 1995. Inscrubed by the author to Loren. A laid in letter from the author to Loren and a Firebrand Books card were removed and are] in Box 2 Folder 63.
Blumenstein, Rosalyne. Branded T. 2003.
Boy's Own. No.40-41, 2003: Apr.-Aug.
Brevard, Aleshia. The Woman I Was Not Born To Be: A Transsexual Journey. Philadelphia: Temple University Press, 2001.
Complot. No.77, July 2003.
FTM Resource Guide. San Francisco: FTM International, 6th ed., Oct. 1999.